# 您看饭的颜色了吗
Do you see the color of this rice?
# 有红的，有黄的，油亮油亮的
It have red and yellow in it. Shiny like oil.
# 手抓饭
Pilaf
# 做手抓饭一定要用羊后腿
We need to use lamb hind shank.
# 作为羊后腿来讲
For the lamb hind shank,
# 吃到嘴里头有一种筋道弹性
it is more springy when you eat it.
# 然后会和米饭的这种弹性
The springiness from the lamb and rice
# 能够特别好的混合
mix well together.
# 那么我们现在把肉做一个
Now, we will prepare the meat
# 简单的一个处理
simply.
# 作为新疆菜来讲是这么一个概念
Xinjiang Cuisine has such concept,
# 新疆菜是比较原始的
It is a bit rustic,
# 粗旷而且好吃
Rustic, but tasty.
# 然后让人看着特别大气
The dishes' appearances are more generous.
# 你知道为什么
Do you know the reason?
# 我刚从新疆回来没有多久
I just came back from Xinjiang.
# 小邓 你这一边说着一边做着
Xiao Deng, you can prepare (the food) while explaining.
# 你这块肉不错
The lamb you brought looks great.
# 大爷你看小邓有点随三叔是吧
Da Ye, do you think Xiao Deng is kinda like San Shu?
# 三叔的徒弟么 有点随三叔
He is the apprentice of San Shu, so it makes sense.
# 这处理之后我们开火
After cutting the lamb, let’s turn on the heat.
# 然后把肉给它飞下水
Then we parboil the lamb.
# 真正在新疆菜原始的做法
Actually, according to the original method,
# 这个是不用飞水的
we don’t need to parboil it.
# 但是如果说不飞水的话
However, without this step,
# 出来以后抓饭颜色会发暗
The color of pilaf will be dark.
# 有一些血沫会出来
Some blood will come out.
# 影响饭的颜色和质地
It will affect the color and texture of the pilaf.
# 这是凉水下锅
We use cold water to parboil.
# 把它稍微的飞下水
We just need to parboil for a few minutes.
# 这里边有几个原材料
There are some ingredients.
# 我给大家简单介绍一下
Let me explain them briefly.
# 第一个原材料大家可能都熟悉了
Our friends may be familiar with the first ingredient.
# 葱头切丝
Let’s julienne the onions.
# 那么这葱头在新疆又叫什么
Do you know what they call “onion” in Xinjiang?
# 又叫皮牙子
They call it “Pi Ya Zi”.
# 这个皮牙子在新疆是唯一的
This “Pi Ya Zi” is the only ingredient in Xinjiang,
# 能够解腻去腥的这么一个原材料
which could be used to reduce greasiness and mask the unpleasant flavor and smell.
# 作为皮牙子来讲
In terms of ‘Pi Ya Zi’,
# 白色的皮牙子略甜不辣
The white ones are a little sweet and not too spicy.
# 紫色的皮牙子是辣中带甜
The purple ones are spicy with a hint of sweetness.
# 紫色的味厚重一点
The flavor of the purple onions is stronger.
# 所以我们采用了两种
Hence, we use two types here.
# 那么除了皮牙子
Besides Pi Ya Zi,
# 还有一个特别重要的原材料
We have another important ingredient.
# 就是胡萝卜和黄萝卜
It is carrot and yellow carrot.
# 其实这点我知道
Actually, I know this.
# 甭看哪儿的胡萝卜都能吃
Even though you can use carrot from anywhere,
# 但是新疆的胡萝卜跟哪的都不一样
The carrots from Xinjiang are distinctive from others.
# 它好吃 尤其是这黄色的
It is tasty, especially the yellow ones.
# 尤其是这黄色的 你尝尝
Especially the yellow one? Try it.
# 脆 胡萝卜那味儿足
Crunchy, it has the strong carrot flavor.
# 北京这胡萝卜它就叫胡萝卜 它没味道
Beijing’s carrot can be called carrot, but it lacks of the flavor.
# 羊肉的品质还是不错的
The quality of this lamb is good.
# 一点肥都没有 全是腱子肉
It didn’t have any fat. It is all tendon and meat.
# 你大爷是最愿吃的 他不爱吃肥的
Da Ye will like this dish. He doesn’t like fat.
# 你看我有一个招你知道吗
I have an idea, do you want to know?
# 其实焯的时候按照你师父的加醋
Based on your master’s habit, you can add some vinegar while parboiling the lamb.
# 你先加上醋好嘞
You can add some vinegar first. Sure.
# 搁点酒可以
We can also add rice wine.
# 现在你还可以加一什么你知道么
Do you know what else you could add in here?
# 加两粒花椒加个大料
Two Sichuan peppercorn, and one star anise.
# 出来那味儿特别香
It will make the lamb smell very good.
# 我觉得二伯有点抢生意
I think Er Bai is taking a little too much control of it.
# 别让你师父知道 背着他师父说
Don’t let your master know. We keep the secret from his master.
# 二伯说什么你要分析着听啊
You should analyze Er Bai’s suggestion.
# 千万不要掉沟里头
Don’t let him lead you to a wrong direction.
# 有时候二伯容易给你刨一坑
Sometimes he may dig a hole and make a trap for you.
# 你就按照你的思维
You can just follow your original thoughts.
# 该搁什么不搁什么
Whether we should or shouldn’t put something in.
# 没事 哎呦
No problem. Ai You!
# 搁点香菜
Add some cilantro.
# 二伯为什么要搁香菜您教我一下
Er bai, could you let me know why we need cilantro here?
# 你闻那味儿 不但去腥味还提鲜了
You can smell it, it not only removes the unpleasant flavor, but also enhances the umami flavor of the lamb.
# 煮一会你看看
Let’s wait to see.
# 你闻这气味都发生变化了
Did you notice? The smell has changed.
# 你比如他们家还有大料
For example, if you have star anise,
# 搁一个就行千万别多
You can put one in, don’t put more than one.
# 借借味儿可香了
Add some flavor, it will smell good.
# 搁几粒花椒别搭理它就行了
Add some Sichuan peppercorns, we just need to leave it there.
# 煮它一会儿
Boil it for a bit.
# 煮它是断生还是煮熟了
Should we cook it until half cooked or totally cooked?
# 别煮完全熟就行
Don’t need to be fully cooked.
# 不煮完全熟
# 对你炒的时候符合你烹饪的要求
You just cook until it satisfies your standard.
# 再煮一会儿 把它香料的味儿释放出来
We need to boil a bit more, so that the spice can release their flavor.
# 新疆做不是这样做
In Xinjiang, they didn’t cook in this way.
# 你又制造了一个新的配方
You are creating a new recipe.
# 好了 关火
OK, turn off the heat.
# 你看这香味就出来了
See, it already smells good.
# 原汤不要了 不要了
Don’t we need the original soup? No, we don’t need it.
# 好把肉我们冲洗一下
Ok, let’s rinse the lamb.
# 这还是热水洗的
The water is warm.
# （用凉水）一下激着了
(If we use cold water) it will make the lamb shrink,
# 它那肉容易变老
Which will make it tough.
# 你再闻一下这肉
You can smell the meat.
# 冲完了什么味都没有
After rinsing it, it doesn’t have any unpleasant smell.
# 看这肉 就是原始的肉的香味了
Only left with the good smell of the lamb.
# 二伯这么一处理 羊肉变成牛肉了
After Er Bai’s modification, the lamb can mimic beef.
# 不带这么刨坑的
Haha, be nice, you dig a hole for me.
# 二伯平时爱创新
Er Bai is very creative.
# 本来你想的是这样做
You had a plan when you started,
# 他会改变你原来的一些方法
He sometimes will change your way to do things.
# 虽然他对我进行抗议 但我该夸的还得夸
Even though he disagrees with me, he deserves the compliments.
# 放点清油
Add some oil.
# 我们老饭骨的精神是什么呢
What’s the spirit of Lao Fan Gu?
# 创新不忘本 传承还不守旧
Be creative but keep the origin in heart, inherit the culture but not restricted by it.
# 二伯他有时候看一些方法上吧
Sometimes, when Er Bai is looking at your methodology,
# 他略微的给你提个醒
He wants to remind you,
# 或者说有一个好的建议
Or maybe provide a good suggestion.
# 但是我为了尊重你本人的意见
But I want to respect your opinion.
# 你就按照原始的做法
You can just follow your own way of cooking.
# 在当中会找出一些
You may find something in this process,
# 那些方面需要调整的
that could be adjusted.
# 油炸 要把肉炸一下
Fry. We need to fry the lamb.
# 把洋葱到里边一起来进行煸炒
Then we add the onion inside, and stir fry.
# 那么炒到了咱们皮牙子变软了
We need to keep frying till the onion is soft,
# 然后味道出来了
and you can smell the aroma.
# 炒到这个味道变得极佳的时候
Stir fry until the flavor becomes the best.
# 这洋葱好吃
The onion tastes good.
# 那我们现在加一点盐
Let’s add some salt.
# 小勺 满勺五克
1 tsp, around 5 g.
# 加完盐之后
After the salt,
# 我们开始放胡萝卜和黄萝卜
Let’s add some carrots and yellow carrots.
# 炒到什么时候
When do we need to stop frying?
# 炒到目前我们胡萝卜和黄萝卜蔫了
Until the carrots are soft.
# 炒软了
Fry until the carrots are soft.
# 倒水 倒清水 三分之一盆
Add some water, around 1/3 of a big bowl.
# 手抓饭么 我们最重要的
Since we are making pilaf, we now need the other important ingredient -
# 另外一个米饭得下锅
Rice. Let’s put rice in the pot.
# 这个米就是我们东北的五常大米
The rice is Wu Chang Rice, from Northeast China.
# 大爷说了 这米要淘的清亮才好
Da Ye told us, the rice should be washed until the water is clear.
# 做出来米饭才透亮
Then the cooked rice will look transparent and clear.
# 我们做抓饭的时候把这米提前泡一下
We need to soak the rice before we start.
# 泡二十五分钟到四十分钟之间
Usually between 25 minutes and 40 minutes.
# 那么我们现在把这个倒到电饭锅里
Let’s put the rice in the rice cooker.
# 看着真香 这汤要倒进去
It looks great, the soup should also be in now.
# 这汤颜色非常好看 黄黄的
The color of this soup is pretty and golden.
# 颜色非常好
The color is good.
# 我们放米饭是朝一个方向
When we put the rice in the rice cooker, we should follow one direction.
# 然后把米一个一个放好
Put the rice in place.
# 要放匀了是吧 把这个米抹平
So the rice should be even? Gently press the rice to be flat on the top.
# 放进去之后
After we put the rice,
# 将汤将将漫过这个 以米为平
The soup should be closed to the level of the rice.
# 稍微略微高一点 略微高一点就行了
The water level is just barely higher than rice. Barely higher.
# 好嘞 现在盖盖子
Ok, now we close the lid.
# 好开始四十分钟
Ok, we then cook for 40 minutes.
# 看看啊 这水使得太对了
See, the water is about right.
# 走了
It is done.
# 看看啊新疆的羊肉手抓饭 漂亮了
See, the Xinjiang Lamb Pilaf. It is pretty.
# 咱们的饭还得加点小料
Our rice also need some other ingredients,
# 葡萄干还有孜然粒
raisins and cumin.
# 然后葡萄干咱们拿水稍微洗一下
Let’s rinse the raisins with water.
# 新疆的葡萄干好吃
Xinjiang’s raisins are tasty.
# 孜然经过处理了么 焙香了
Did you do anything with cumin? I toasted it lightly.
# 然后我们又给它擀到半碎
Then crushed it into coarse grinds.
# 全碎的话会影响口感
If it's in fine grinds, the texture is not ideal.
# 均匀的撒在上面
Sprinkle on the top evenly.
# 手抓饭好家伙
Lamb pilaf, very good.
# 要把它拌开
Then we need to mix it.
# 现在呢我们先干一件事
Now we need to do one thing.
# 把我们的刚才肉挑出来之后
For the lamb we picked it out previously,
# 咱们上的时候放在边上
We will put it on the side of the plate when we serve the dish.
# 羊肉改改刀么 改改刀
Should we cut the lamb to smaller pieces? Yes, we need to do that.
# 这羊肉为什么之前
Why?
# 不把它改小一点
Why didn’t we cut it smaller previously?
# 咱们这抓饭是需要一个
Because we need to cook the pilaf
# 将近四十分钟的一个时间
For more than 40 minutes.
# 如果你把块改小了之后
If you cut it to smaller pieces,
# 时间长了以后羊肉的太烂了
It will be too soft and may break apart during this long cooking period.
# 口感有变化
It changes the texture.
# 听到了吧 为什么羊肉不改小块
See? That's why we didn't cut the lamb into small pieces earlier.
# 然后现在你看我们把饭拌匀
Now we will mix the rice and other ingredients.
# 我们再加上葡萄干
Put the raisins in.
# 新疆人吃饭真是讲究
People in Xinjiang put a lot of thoughts in this dish.
# 您看饭的颜色了吗
Have you seen the color of this rice?
# 慢慢的有红的有黄的
Slowly, it has red and yellow color.
# 而且饭又经过了肉的汤汁的
The rice has absorbed the meat juice.
# 这种浸泡 油亮油亮的
After soaking in it, the oil makes it shiny.
# 盛一份我们的抓饭
Take a portion of the pilaf.
# 码一份让网友们看看好
Show our online friends how to plate.
# 这盘抓饭放在这儿
Let’s leave the rest here,
# 然后我们现在再做另外一个处理
And we will do one more thing -
# 羊肉切成大丁好了
Cut the lamb to big chunks.
# 尝尝啊给个评价好不好吃
Try it. How is the taste?
# 太好吃了是吧
It is super delicious, isn’t it?
# 我你得拍我 你不拍我怎么吃
You should focus on me, how could I try without you shooting me?
# 你老拍地是吧
You like shooting the floor, aren’t you?
# 好吃吧 二伯真好吃
Is it great? Er bai, it is really good.
# 羊肉一点膻味都没有
The lamb doesn’t have the unpleasant smell and flavor.
# 而且整个感觉会特别好
It tastes really good as a whole.
# 饭的整个口味略带咸甜
The rice is salty and a bit sweet.
# 您觉得不够咸的话
If you think it needs more salt,
# 也可以再给点盐都行
You could add some (based on your own taste).
# import ending.sbv 0:08:52.400